<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An old bridle for a vvilde asse-colt. Or, the new mystery of iniquity unfolded, briefely discovering the physiognomy of a wanton youthfull king, carnall reason, who under the name of true reason bewitcheth, and deceiveth many unstable soules; for those whose sakes is here declared their cunning wiles, and flights; by which they do deceive, and draw disciples after them, to their own perpetuall disgrace, if not destruction. In a briefe commentary on the second of Peter, chap. 2. Where the apostle hath plainly prophesied  of that sort of antichristians, or false prophets, now commonly known by the name of ranters, whose unreasonable practises being only named, and laid open to view, wil be sufficient ground to reasonable men, to desert their wicked wayes, and societies, which they continue so infectious and disorderd. / By Raunce Burthall.</title>
            <author>Burthall, Raunce.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E615_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865675</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E615[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An old bridle for a vvilde asse-colt. Or, the new mystery of iniquity unfolded, briefely discovering the physiognomy of a wanton youthfull king, carnall reason, who under the name of true reason bewitcheth, and deceiveth many unstable soules; for those whose sakes is here declared their cunning wiles, and flights; by which they do deceive, and draw disciples after them, to their own perpetuall disgrace, if not destruction. In a briefe commentary on the second of Peter, chap. 2. Where the apostle hath plainly prophesied  of that sort of antichristians, or false prophets, now commonly known by the name of ranters, whose unreasonable practises being only named, and laid open to view, wil be sufficient ground to reasonable men, to desert their wicked wayes, and societies, which they continue so infectious and disorderd. / By Raunce Burthall.</title>
                  <author>Burthall, Raunce.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Stephen Dagnall, Bookseller at Alsbury,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct: 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Raunce Burthall is a pseudonym.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ranters --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN OLD BRIDLE FOR A Wilde Aſſe-Colt.</p>
            <p>OR, The new myſtery of iniquity unfolded, briefely diſcovering the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiognomy of a wanton youthfull King. <hi>Carnall Reaſon,</hi> Who under the name of true Reaſon bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and deceiveth many unſtable ſoules; for whoſe ſakes is here declared their cunning wiles, and ſlights; by which they do deceive, and draw Diſciples after them, to their own perpetuall diſgrace, if not deſtruction.</p>
            <p>In a briefe Commentary on the ſecond of <hi>Peter,</hi> Chap. 2. Where the Apoſtle hath plainly propheſied of that ſort of Antichriſtians, or falſe prophets, now commonly known by the name of <hi>Ranters;</hi> whoſe unreaſonable practiſes being only named, and laid open to view, wil be ſufficient ground to reaſonable men, to deſert their wicked wayes, and ſocieties, which they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſo infections and diſorderd.</p>
            <q>Avoid them as an alluring Strumpet.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Proverbs 5.8.</bibl>
               <p>Remove thy way far from her, come not nigh the doore of her houſe.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom 16. 18.</bibl>
               <p>They that are ſuch, ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by good words, and faire ſpeeches, deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By RAUNCE BURTHALL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Stephen Dagnall,</hi> Bookſeller at <hi>Alſbury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165756:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was a ſad complaint of the Lord againſt Iſrael, <hi>Ezekiel, 2.7.</hi> and thou ſhalt ſpeak my words unto them, whether they will forbeare, For they are Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Whether the perſons in this Treatiſe deſcribed may be thus Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteriſed, conſider for thy ſatisfaction the reaſon of Gods calling the Jſraelites by the aforeſaid name, <hi>viz.</hi> their refuſing to heare, and obey tje word of the Lord, and verily if ever people did thus offend, ſurely theſe that are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this diſcourſe are not innocent, for has not the Lord ſpoken to theſe men by that Law of nature, mentioned <hi>Romans</hi> the <hi>2.14, 15?</hi> have they not conſcience accuſing, or excuſing? ſurely if they have not, it is becauſe they have ſo long ſinned againſt their conſciences, that they are become ſeared with an hot Jron, <hi>1 Tim. 4.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Has not the Lord ſpoken to them by the Prophets, yea, by his Son; and doe they not refuſe <hi>to heare</hi> while they ſay of his word, it is no <hi>Rule to them?</hi> did Jſrael deſpiſe it more, <hi>2 Chro. 36.16?</hi> or the ſtiffe-necked in <hi>Acts 7.51.</hi> or ſome among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in ſaying? that there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead, <hi>1 Corinth, 15.12?</hi> or <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> in ſaying the Reſurrection is paſt already, <hi>2 Tim. 2.17, 18?</hi> or the ſcoffers mentioned in the <hi>2</hi> of <hi>Peter 3.4, 5?</hi> in ſaying where is the promiſe of his comming, and that all things continne as they were from the beginning of the creation? or theſe that walk in the luſt of uncleanneſſe, deſpiſing government, <hi>2 Per. 2.10?</hi> or the covetous, the proud, the boaſters, the falſe accuſers, the incontinent, the fierce, the deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, the lovers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, more then the lovers of God, <hi>2 Tim. 3.2.3, 4.</hi> Certainly if the Jſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites were called by the name of rebellion, for refuſing to heare the voyce of the Lord in the Law and the Prophets; then thoſe that now refuſe to heare his voyce in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw, the Prophets, and in the Goſpell of his Son, may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called by the ſame name And as earthly governours doe not indure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in their dominions, but do caſt them our by death or otherwiſe, no more will the Lord ſuffer theſe that despiſe his Law, and yeeld no obediènce to it, to injoy any protection from him. <hi>Thoſe mine enemies that would not that I ſhould Reigne over them, bring hither and ſlay them before me,</hi> Luke <hi>19 27.</hi> Yea, he will come in <hi>flaming fire taking vengeance on them that obey not the Goſpell, 2</hi> Theſ. <hi>1.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader let the conſideration of this move thee to take compaſſion of thoſe that have brought themſelves ſo neare deſtruction, even as Chriſt did over the City Jeruſalem when he beheld it, and wept over it, <hi>Luke 19.41, 42.</hi> and if thou wilt inlarge that which is briefely declared in this following Treatiſe, thou maiſt happily be an Inſtrument of turning many ſo righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which will be well rewarded, even with everlaſting Glory as bright as the Stars.<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note> Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165756:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>sun and clouds</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene the portion of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even in all ages, to be peſtered with falſe prophets, and that of divers ſorts, ſome of longer continuance, That have acted like princes, carrying on their intereſt with great pompe, and Applauſe, from the world: yea with ſuch authority as if they were infallible, and under the name of true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, have beene all along true perſecutors of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. But theſe I hope are neere their tropicke, and their date almoſt expired: for did their Arme of fleſh, (the powers of the world) withdraw their aſſiſtance from them, they could not long ſtand: for their whole ſtrength depending thereupon, it would ſpoile their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. The true Church of Chriſt hath altogether her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on the ſpirit of Chriſt, to carry on her deſigne, although the earthly powers oppoſe them: but the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church being ſufficiently inſtructed where her ſtrengh lyes, depends on the Arme of fleſh as her chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pillar whereon to worke her deſigne: but when that prop failes her, the chiefeſt flower in her garden is gone.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort of falſe Prophets, and whom I make the ſubject of this diſcourſe, are ſuch that have beene very eminent (at leaſt ſome of them) very beautifull and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious profeſſors of the goſpell, ſo that in appearance to all men (yea and to the Saints,) Chriſt was their end both in profeſſion and converſation. Why whats the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165756:3"/>matter is it not ſo ſtill? I could heartily wiſh and ſhould much rejoyce it were ſo. But alas they? are fallen, they are downe, they are bewitcht, I had almoſt ſaid doubly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witcht, with white, and black: witneſſe, their high and and eminent expreſſions, even to admiration, one while: and in a moment curſe and ſweare like Bedlams: Is this the ſpirit of reformation? Is this reſtoring the creature from its fall, to its primitive excellency, they pretend ſo indeed, but it appeares otherwiſe: verily I cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe beleeve, but that if God had ſent them, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>florers, he would have gone before them, and carried them out ſo, as they ſhould have made better proceedings; Chriſt ſaith, all that ever came before me are the eves, and Robbers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.8, <hi>Exod</hi> 33.15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.2.</note> And Moſes was of the ſame minde, ſaying to God, if thou goe not before us, carry us not hence. Nay an Angell of Gods owne ſending, did not ſatisfie him, and the people; except Gods owne preſence accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied: Then take we heed theſe Men deceive us not: who would make us believe, that they are ſome of thoſe Angells, ſpoken of in the Revelation, to goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; truly I am full of Chriſts and Moſes minde, I had rather have Gods owne preſence to goe before us, then be troubled with ſuch Angells. For if he goe before us, I am ſure there will be no curſing, nor ſwearing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, but rather Hallelujahs, bleſſing and prayſing God for ſuch reſtitutions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6.</note> ſaying, the Lord god omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Reigneth.</p>
            <p>Yea but do theſe people indeede reſtore, as they ſay they doe: why, what doe they reſtore, can they take off the curſe from the earth, that it bring not forth briers thornes: can they reſtore women from paines in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, can they deliver the creatures, (as Beevs and mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons &amp;c.) from being killed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> to be our foode: and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them alſo from divers other vanities they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected under by God, for the time being. If they can, why then do they ſuffer (Beeves &amp; muttons &amp;c.) or ſo much as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165756:3"/>a chicke to be killed for them to partake off:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.29.</note> why doe they not live upon herbes onely, nay doe not theſe men plainely declare their pride in making themſelves wiſer then God, in attempting to overthrow that order his wiſedome hath ſet here below, untill fallen man be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which is far beyond their power to effect, though not beyond their pride to attempt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But ſay they, we muſt reſtore as farre as we can, and leave that which we cannot doe, to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I An. it is well they have ſome manners, But I ſhould have judged better of them and their manners alſo, had they with <hi>Moſes</hi> taken God to goe before them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But ſay they, we are reſtored already, and now is the time, for we are reſtored to ſuch perfection that we cannot ſinne. And even as that vanity which is upon the creatures came for mans ſake, even ſo we being reſtored, the creatures of right are reſtored.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Stay a little, one ſwallow makes not a Summer: it doth not follow that all men are reſtored, although it were true that they were, which is falſe.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly I anſwer, if they would ſpeak truely,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</note> and in ſtead of reſtored ſay, they are returned ſo as <hi>Peter</hi> makes mention of, namely, that the dog is returned to his owne vomit againe, and the ſow that was waſhed to her wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the mire: then I ſhall beleeve their returne: and all that know them, will confeſſe the ſame: or had they further dealt plainely and ſaid, that they had beene reſtorers of that old ſect called the <hi>Adamites,</hi> the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of love, the old opinions of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and the <hi>Nicholaitans:</hi> I ſhould likewiſe have beleeved them: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept onely theſe may be ſuppoſed to be ſomewhat wilder, and doe ſomewhat outſtrip thoſe their predeceſſors, in looſneſſe, and prophaneſſe: But becauſe the Apoſtles, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Iude,</hi> expreſly ſpeake of ſuch a kinde of men as theſe are: let us heare a little their deſcriptions: I ſhall ſpeake onely of ſome verſes.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165756:4"/>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>2. <hi>Peter</hi> 2.2. <hi>And many ſhall follow their pernicious wayes, by reaſon of whom, the way of truth ſhalbe blaſphemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve here, the Prophets are bad, and their wayes are bad, the Prophets are falſe, and their wayes pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, its very dangerous following blind and falſe guides, yet theſe falſe Prophets ſhall have many followers. The way of truth ſuffers deepely by them, for it is evill ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and blaſphemed: now whether our falſe Prophets blaſpheme the way of truth or not, that ſo wee may not wrong them, conſider. If you ſpeake to them of the ſcriptures:<note place="margin">1 Concerning the Scriptures.</note> they will tell you, they would not ſo much as make uſe of them: but becauſe of you to whom they ſpeake, they are above them, and beyond them, but where I know not, nor themſelves neither: but I am ſure that they are without them, and their teſtimony. Againe, if you ſpeake of Religion,<note place="margin">2 Concerning Religion.</note> and holineſſe, they will tell you, their worke is to drive men out of religion, and holineſſe, and their way to effect it, is by ſwearing and curſing: but whither drive they? verily I know not; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to the Devill, their now intimate companion, for he that we call the devill, is become their God, and they are not afraid to tell you, that they had as liefe to keepe company with the devell as with God: but in concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on they will tell you, there is no devill at all. Speake to them of preaching,<note place="margin">3 Concerning preaching.</note> or holding forth the truth, they will tell you, that the greateſt preachers, are the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luders: but they muſt except themſelves, for they are the greateſt deluders of all, which appears thus: thoſe men that allow of preaching doe ingeniouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it a meanes in ſubordination to the ſpirit of God, adminiſtring good to the hearers: but contrariwiſe theſe men deny preaching, and yet practiſe that which is equivalent, in their occaſionall meetings: namely, they communncate one to another both by word, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and like men infected with the plague, they catch the diſeaſe one of another: I meane their corrupt opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165756:4"/>and practiſes: and yet not withſtanding, you muſt believe if you can, that it is all from the ſpirit, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly, without meanes, all meanes are below their ſpheare, they are above all meanes, and truth too: now is not this a pretty Juggling? are not theſe the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious deceivers? but I would ſeriouſly demand of theſe men, whether they never enjoyed any living influences from God, in the uſe of meanes: namely goſpell duties, and ſpirituall exerciſes, or did God never ordaine any formes, or meanes or have they diſſembled all this while, &amp; now only come to a right poſture; if it be ſo that they are above and beyond all formall enjoyments, inſomuch as formes are uſeleſſe; then let them know they muſt not ſo much as ſpeake together concerning<note n="*" place="margin">And if men may not by ſpeaking com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat about Religion, then why did God give men gifts for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God gives nothing in vaine.</note> God, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: for its formall, whatſoever they doe: and all this while they have diſſembled and coſened o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers: but themſelves moſt: but however theſe delude themſelves, true believers have and doe know the joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſound, in formes and meanes, waiting on God, till higher enjoyments come. But where do we finde, any one inſtance of Prophet, Apoſtle, or Saint, that did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver curſe and ſweare men out of their Religion, and formes: the Goſpell ſaints did not ſo to the Iewes, and their formes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.15.</note> but rather buried with honour thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable corpſes, and were aboundant in condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of love to the weake brethren, even after God had left thoſe formes, and their date was expired.</p>
            <p>Verſe 10. <hi>they deſpiſe government:</hi> &amp;c. They know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that feare of law, and freedom to ſin;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10.</note> cannot ſtand together, do therefore deſpiſe the lawes of men: that ſo they might the better without controle, accompliſh their luſts: therefore to evade that, they labour to make men believe, that the law, by which all men ſhould now be guided, is within all men, which law they call, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and alſo their King: but when I conſider what a Lord of miſrule their King is: among themſelves,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165756:5"/>men muſt be very wary, of voting up this King, into the throne.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14, 15.</note> I rather incline to Gods counſell, which <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> exhorts to, promoting a viſible lawfull government among men, during the time appointed by God; then ſubmit to their inviſible, preſumptuous, and ſelfe-will'd King,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10.</note> untill their young king Reaſon, obtaines a riper Iudgement, and his ſubjects a more rationall and civill deportment. And ſhall alſo earneſtly deſire, they may never have,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 8.</note> any filthy dreames, or viſions, tending that way: for tis a ſure tenent, that a good outward government, conſtituted, with good and wholeſome lawes, was never eſteemed by Godly men obnoxious, or a burthen, and bondage to any, but to evill men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 13. And ſhall receive the reward of unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp;c. they ſay there is, no unrighteousneſſe: but in our conceits; and conſequently no ſuch thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded: I ſuppoſe they would have it ſo; but <hi>Iohns</hi> opinion, and theirs, differs; he ſaith, If we ſay we have no ſinne,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8.10.</note> we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us, and we make him a liar, for ſaying ſo of us, if it be not ſo: but the truth is our unrighteous actions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare plainly, that we neither have ſeene him, nor knowne him,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Job.</hi> 3.6.</note> (namely Chriſt Jeſus) therefore they are ſtrange Children, that can ſinne, becauſe grace hath abounded, and that it may abound the more, ſuch are growne very skil-ful, they have learned how to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Pauls Interrogatories, how ſhall we that are dead to ſin live any longer therein? It is true indeed in a ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall conſideration, that hath beene ſinne heretofore, which is not ſin now, but it is farre otherwiſe upon a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall account, for even now, in the time of the goſpell, we are under the law to Chriſt;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.21.</note> now where a law is, there is a poſſibility of trangreſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 13. Yea but are theſe ſo unreaſonable as to riot in the day time, and count it pleaſure ſo to doe: I could wiſh they had not left me without Apologie for them,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165756:5"/>in that behalfe they have even almoſt (if not altogether) caſt off all ſhame, its a trouble to them, to thinke of being aſhamed: to abſtaine from all appearance of evill, is to much niceneſſe with them, their Stomackes are not ſo queaſie, their worke is chiefely to offend men, touching Religion, and except they make evill to appeare openly, their worke goes not kindely on: therefore they will drink, and tipple and ſweare like mad, and that you may know they account it pleaſure, they wil ſing merrily, their amorous ditties: how ever it hath happened ſo it is come to paſſe, that there are divers of Balaams Aſſes amongſt us, that have for ſome time beene Ridden and burthen'd with ſuch balamitiſh Prophets: but I hope ere long, God will open the mouth of theſe Aſſes, to ſpeake with mans voice, (namely reaſon to forbid the madnes of theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.) Now what ſpots &amp; blemiſhes theſe are to all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, and ſober minded men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</note> to feaſt or keep compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny withall: I leave to any man to Iudge, that hath not loſt, and buried, his Reaſon amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Now how they ſport themſelves with their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings they doe it thus: they will looke upon you ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, and ſay: I made thee &amp;c. But upon your deniall to make their words true they will ſay, (<hi>I am made thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">I can upon ſufficient proofe, make good what I charge them withall.</note>) Againe they will ſay by Gods blood thou art redeemed, And by God I will doe ſo, or ſo, then if you diſlike their ſpeakings, as I know not who can like them, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, conſidering their manner of the expreſſions, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the form and manner of an oath, then they would ſalve it thus, ſaying, are ye not redeemed, by the blood of God: and muſt I not doe all by Gods helpe: and thus they turne many precious truths, into oaths and Riddles: and make a Ieſt of them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 13.</note> and ſo ſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their owne deceivings. And is not this fine hocus pocus, you know a liar hath ever more a purpoſe to deceive, and theſe doe the ſame, by their owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: But if they would thus ſalve their ſwearing, and would not have us thinke they ſweare, then why doe they labour to defend ſwearing, by quoting divers places
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165756:6"/>of ſcripture, to maintaine it? Now ſeeing they Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gize one while, that it might not ſeeme ſwearing, &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other while maintaine the lawfulneſſe of ſwearing, they are plaine deluders, they agree with the truth like harpe and harrow.</p>
            <p>Verſe 14. Having eyes full of Adultery: now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning bodily Adultery: thats become a ſtrange thing, they will acknowledge none but ſpirituall adultery: they are ſo confirmed in their opinion that way, that they make that their hackney to lead on to the other, which they call no Adultery. But what, is Marrying become Null? Are thoſe neereſt relations ceaſed? Its very ſtrange that Chriſt was no better inſtructed, then to publiſh doctrines that were to have no longer continnuance: did he make that neere relation of husband and wife to hold forth the neere conjunction, and relation betwixt the Church and himſelfe: and the love of the one the love of the other, with many other mutuall reſpects:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.23, 24, 25.</note> and are they now ceaſed? Old <hi>Tertullian</hi> could ſay, and that rightly, of nothing, there is no metaphor: Now if there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality in ſuch relations, Chriſt muſt come again, and teach us truer doctrine, if he will have us believe him; but we need not wonder at their nullifying goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doctrines; for by this it appears plainly, that they nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify natures law, and go beyond <hi>Adams</hi> ruins, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend repaire, where was no decay: therefore let theſe repairers know, if they are not wilfully blinde, that marriage was inſtituted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.21, 22, 23, 24.</note> in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>adiſe, before mans fall: And ſo it is not a law that belongs to mans fallen eſtate, but alſo to his eſtate in innocency; to confirme this the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> brings in a Reaſon, founded upon the Creation, declaring wherefore God made but one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for one man, although God had the reſidue of the Spirit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.15.</note> and could have made more, had it been agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his divine will; the reaſon ſaith <hi>Malachi</hi> was, that he might ſeeke a Godly ſeed, and not a baſtardly, illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate broode, which muſt needs have followed, and now would alſo, if either <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> or <hi>Nicholas</hi> his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165756:6"/>ſhould take place, as theſe their ſucceſſors, would have it. Doth not the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> expreſly call for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to Marry a doctrine of Devills,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.3.</note> ſo that it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears, that the devill and not God, taught theſe ſeducing ſpirits this doctrine? Hath not God plainly ſtamped this in nature? doth not the bird chooſe his mate, and both together bring up their young? Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans write ſtrange things, concerning the ſwan, in caſe of wrong that way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection</hi> Mat. 22.30 <hi>In the reſurrection</hi> men <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther marry nor are given in marriage, but are as the Angells of God:</hi> from this place they would conclude, that this reſurrection is now, and ſo there is now no right of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, or giving in Marryage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I deſire them, firſt, to Conſider their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, the Sadduces, that firſt framed this objection: and their end in ſo doing, which was to overthrow the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body: ſo that the reſurrection of the ſoule in the ſtate of grace, here cannot be meant, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeaks he of ſuch a ſtate of men and women, that had not firſt died the naturall death, but of thoſe ſeven men and that one woman, that were dead and buryed, ſaying whoſe wife ſhall ſhe be of the ſeven, for all ſeven had her to wife? Now ſuch as the death ſpoken of here is, ſuch is the reſurrection, that ſtands in oppoſition: which is plainly that of the body. And whereas it is fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther ſaid, they are as the Angells of God, it is evidently knowne that Angels doe not procreat; then let them ceaſe to breake of Relations during the time of procreation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they are ceaſed to be reaſonable men.</p>
            <p>Verſe 14. And cannot ceaſe to ſinne. I know not well how they ſhould ceaſe to ſinne, when themſelves would be lawleſſe, for they making good and evill, God and the devill all one, what ceſſation from ſin can be expected? Therefore the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> againe, hath hath this additionall deſcription of them: ſaying, yee have wearied the Lord, with your words, yet ye ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2.17.</note> wherein have we wearied him? He Anſwers them thus,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165756:7"/>when ye ſay, every one that doth evill, is good, in the ſight of the Lord, &amp; he delights in them, mark here how they delude themſelvs, although they act ſin and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they thinke God accounts them good, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in them too: Oh what a blinding ſinne is this breaking of Relations: which <hi>Malachi</hi> taxeth them of here, I will cloſe this with <hi>Aſaphs</hi> words, ſaith God: theſe things haſt thou done, &amp; I kept ſilence, thou thoughteſt that I was altogether<note n="*" place="margin">Some of them ſtick not to ſay that Chriſt was a <hi>Ranter.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</note> ſuch an one as thy ſelf;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50, 51.</note> but I will reprove thee, and ſet thy ſins in order, before thine eyes.</p>
            <p>Verſe 14. <hi>beguileing unſtable ſoules.</hi> Mark well what people are miſled by them, they are unſtable ſoules, ſuch as were newly out of the ſhell, of a carnall ſtate, a little eſcaped from them, who live in errour: as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes they are ſilly people, that are ſo led, but moſt ſilly to continue long ſo led; for when once the depth of their wicked wayes, is perceived by an ingenious ſpirit: he cannot but forſake both them and their wayes: except he be willing to bury his reaſon, and become a wicked man, and a foole both at once.</p>
            <p>Verſe 14. An heart they have exerciſed with Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous practiſes, one would thinke this could not touch them at all: for they account nothing their owne, but all things common: but if you were but a little acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them, as ſome are: to their coſt. You ſhould find that to be but their develliſh cunning namly: to teach you to account nothing<note n="*" place="margin">They ſay propriety is a devill, but whether it be a deviliſh ſpeech, yea, or no, conſider theſe places of Scripture. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.7. to 12. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.33, 34, 35. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8.9. With many more.</note> yours: that ſo they might with this Engine in a very ſhort ſpace deprive you of all you have. Oh what quicke returnes have they in their journeyes, to ſuch places, and houſes, where their lanck bellies, and purſes, are made Plump, they, make hay while the ſunne ſhines: for feare leaſt their beguiled Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſhould throw off their burthen, too ſoone.</p>
            <p>Verſe 17 <hi>Wells without water.</hi> They would have you thinke them deeply learned, in divine miſteries, when as its but the miſtery of iniquity: new guilt over, even their white witchery, (called the deepneſſe of ſatan in the Revelation) which can never ſalve the wounds their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165756:7"/>black witchery makes, namely their Curſings, Swearings, Riotings, &amp;c. they make ſhew of waters indeed becauſe they are ſtiled wells, but if you aſſay and let downe your bucket,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.5.</note> like a man of underſtanding as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, (where counſell in the heart of man, is likned to deepe waters,) and by<note n="*" place="margin">As the Queen of <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> proved <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> wiſdom and parts.</note> wiſe and prudent queſtions gage their depth: there will come up nothing but dirt and ſtones; there is no waters to refreſh you, but mudde to Choake you.</p>
            <p>Iude <hi>Verſe</hi> 13. <hi>He there calls them wandering ſtarres.</hi> This holds forth their Phiſiognomy, as clearly as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the childs that is like him, no Limner can draw ſhape ſo neere his patterne, if you come to a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and aske him where he dwelles, he will ſay he hath ſmall dwelling, whereas when you have well examined the matter he hath the largeſt dwelling of all for he dwels every where, ſo theſe wandring unfixed ſtarres, as they are like, ſo they are the boldeſt of all, beggers; for where ever they come they are at home ſtill; tis all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon where they graze: now ye know wandring ſtarres, are bad guides, to ſeamen, and travellers: onely the fixed ſtarres, are ſerviceable to men, even to ſuch men that ſtay at home, in their callings, like fixed ſtarres; and are not inordinate buſſie-bodies, but do with quietneſſe work and eate there one bread, are profitable to themſelves, and others: but theſe wandring ſtars; are uſeleſſe both at home and abroad, they ſhine, deceitfully. They guide falſly, but devour truely, all that truſt them, both in their ſoules and bodies, but as wandring ſtarres, blaze, and inſtantly vaniſh and appeare no more, ſo will theſe goe out ere long, like the ſnuffe of a candle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 18. <hi>They ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity &amp;c.</hi> Obſerve here, they are but words, they are not true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, their words are great, and ſwelling they break over all former bounds, and limits, both of nature, and Religion: they are all ſpirit, full of viſions, and revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on they are rapt up into the third heaven. Higher then <hi>Paul</hi> was, but with this difference, <hi>Paul</hi> heard things
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165756:8"/>unutterable, but theſe have great utterance for their wares, with ſtrong lines and high expreſſions, even to amazement;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.5.11.24.</note> but our Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> here leads us out of that maze, ſtiling them, ſwelling words of vanity. Theſe are they,<note place="margin">They openly acknowledge themſelves to be Chriſt.</note> ſpoken of by Chriſt himſelfe, ſaying many ſhall come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt and ſhall deceive many, yea if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceive the very elect, they are very cunning; therefore take heed, you poore deluded ſoules, looke well to your ſtanding, look how you are bottomed, and principled, for if your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion come from no higher riſe then man, theſe cunning men will robbe you of it, for they profeſſe it to be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry end, and ſcope, of their meſſage: they will curſe and ſweare you out of all, and leave you as void of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as themſelves, even no more Religion then a wild Bull. And alas poore ſoules, even theſe deluders themſelves, are Retrograde, even gone backe many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, below the firſt heaven, and ſo have created trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vexation to themſelves: they muſt for all their proud looks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.</note> come to their ABC. againe even the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Doctrine of Chriſt: And lay againe the foundation of repentance, from dead works, and of faith towards God, and be glad they ſpeed no worſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 19. <hi>While they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption &amp;c.</hi> The wits of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells contracted, and united into one; could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly invent ſo many evident, and cleare deſcriptions of theſe wilde Kine. Theſe are the true libertines, the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture makes mention off, and oppoſes, although it hath too long been, the portion of the truly Godly, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe that reproach: let therefore, Godly men, have their white Robes reſtored, and given to them, <hi>(viz.)</hi> let their innocency, be reſtored, by thoſe, who have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken it from them; and let the ſaddle be laid upon the right Horſe; time, and action, hath made manifeſt who they are; even thoſe that have turned ſpirituall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty into carnall, and themſelves out of all Religion into beaſtiality. But what fooles, or rather mad men are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165756:8"/>theſe, that dare undertake to promiſe others liberty; when they themſelves, are ſuch fettered ſlaves, and Goale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> birds? Nay, their God, (the devil I mean,) is kept faſt in everlſtaingChaines, under darkneſſe; unto the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great day; and how then can theſe his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects promiſe others freedom, and their Maſter Chained up?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> We aknowledge onely one power; and ſo there is no devill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We acknowledge likewiſe but one omnipotent, eternal power, in whom, all finite, created exiſtencies live, and move, and have their beings; we confeſſe all action, as it is action, (even in devils) is of God, and ſo tis good; but how can this free either devils, or men, that are ſubjected, under a Law; for their actions, muſt not be meere actions, but regular, according to Law. Now in reſpect of God, all is good that's acted, or can be acted, by men or devils; yet the ſame action that is good, in, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, may be very evil and wicked, in reſpect of men, and devils; becauſe the Lawes rectitude was not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, but violated; witneſſe, the words of <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Iohn;</hi> both <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Pontitus Pilate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.27, 28. A like inſtance 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11,12. Here God acts, and man acts; the one well, the other ill, in the ſame work.</note> &amp;c. Were gathered together for to doe whatſoever thy hand, and thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell determined before to be done; yet what good was in <hi>Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in betraying; and <hi>Herod,</hi> and the reſt, in putting Chriſt to death; except their end, and ſcope, had been one and the ſame, with Gods own will and power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting? tis true, the work which they did was very good, but not as done by them; but onely in reſpect of him, who brings good out of evill; ſo that all the good that was in it, is Gods; all the evill attending it, is theirs; and what elſe was that but their covetouſneſſe, malice, and envy, that ſet them to work, to do all they did. Thus we ſee tis very plaine, that there is one holy power, acting nothing but good, and a corrupt power as devils and wicked men, acting nothing but evill, ſuch as theſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal libertines are (with whom I conteſt;) and whoſe ſeducing wayes, I admoniſh all to beware off, that are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165756:9"/>not willing to be blinded, and to live in fellowſhip with the devill; and as it is moſt true, that Antichriſtians are leaſt ſenſible what Antichriſtianiſme is, even ſo theſe mens frequent employment, and communion with the devil, hath ſo infatuated &amp; benumed their ſenſes, that they falſely conceit and conclude, there is no devil, although they are his vaſſels to do his will at every beck. Againe, I ſay beware of theſe ſpirit mongers; that their fair pretences, beguile you not; as I have heard many young people and children, have been in <hi>London;</hi> by men called ſpirits, who cunningly, by faire pretences and promiſes. ſteale them away, and ſell them for ſlaves; never dreame ye that theſe men can bring you to freedome, when themſelves are ſo deep over head and eares in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; remember <hi>Peters</hi> excellent reaſon,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. v. 19.</note> 
               <hi>(viz.) For of whom a man is overcome, of the ſame is be brought in bondage.</hi> I ſhall by way of Caution, ſhut up all with two Places of Scripture.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</note> Firſt, that of <hi>Peter, it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them not to have knowne the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then after they have knowne it, to turne from the holy Commandement delivered unto them:</hi> The other place is Chriſts own words, and miſerable doome, upon Revolters;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.43, 44, 45.</note> 
               <hi>when the uncleane ſpirit is gone out of a man; he walketh through dry places, ſeeking reſt, and findeth none; then he ſaith, I will returne into my houſe, from whence I came out; and when he is come, hee fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it empty, ſwept, and garniſhed: then goeth hee and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with himſelfe, ſeven other ſpirits, more wicked then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and they enter in and dwell there; and the laſt eſtate of that man, is worſe then the firſt; even ſo ſhall it be unto this wicked generation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
